خلنير، قرية سورية جميلة بنيت على الضفة الشمالية لواد يخترقها
من الجنوب الشرقي باتجاه الشمال الغربي.
Khilneer, a beautiful Syrian village built on the northern
bank of a valley that cuts through it from the southeast
towards the northwest.
وهي تقع شمال غرب مدينة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي بخمسة
كيلومترات، كما أنها تقع شمال غرب مدينة حلب بخمسة وستين
كيلومتراً.
It is located 5 kilometers northwest of the city of Afrin in
the northern countryside of Aleppo, and 65 kilometers
northwest of the city of Aleppo.
تطل من جهتها الغربية الجنوبية على سهل جوم، سكانها الأوائل من
الأكراد السوريين الذين قدموا إليها منذ أكثر من ستمائة عام،
It overlooks the Joum plain from its southwestern side. Its
first inhabitants were Syrian Kurds who came to it more than
600 years ago,
وسكنوا في المغارات التي تحيط فيها من جهاتها الأربع.
and lived in the caves that surround it on all four sides.
يسكنها حالياً أكثر من مئة عائلة من سكانها الأصليين، إضافة
إلى عوائل سورية مهجرة قسراً من كافة المناطق المختلفة.
It is currently inhabited by more than 100 families of its
original inhabitants, in addition to Syrian families
forcibly displaced from all different regions.
يعتمد سكانها في حياتهم على الزراعة وتربية المواشي وعلى تجارة
الحبوب والزيت وعلى بعض المهن والحرف،
Its inhabitants rely for their livelihood on agriculture,
livestock breeding, the trade of grain and oil, and some
professions and crafts.
حيث يوجد فيها أكثر من سبعين ألف شجرة زيتون إضافة إلى
ثلاثمائة رأس من الأغنام والماعز.
There are more than 70,000 olive trees in it, in addition to
300 heads of sheep and goats.
يوجد فيها مدرسة ابتدائية واحدة تعود إلى عام ألف وتسعمائة
وسبعين، إضافة إلى معصرة زيتون واحدة،
It has one primary school dating back to 1970, in addition
to one olive press.
وترتفع فيها نسبة التعليم وحملة الشهادات الجامعية من كافة
التخصصات.
The literacy rate and the number of university degree
holders in all specializations are high.
يتميز أهلها بالفطرة الطيبة وكرم الضيافة والطبيعة القاسية في
نفس الوقت.
Its people are characterized by their good nature,
hospitality, and a tough nature at the same time.
تاريخياً هناك روابط اجتماعية مشتركة بين قرية خلنير وقريتي
كفرشيل وجويق، الكل ينتمون إلى عشيرة كردية واحدة.
Historically, there are common social ties between the
village of Khilneer and the villages of Kfarsheel and Jweik,
all belonging to one Kurdish tribe.
أهالي القرية قدموا إلى هنا منذ أكثر من ستمائة عام. للحديث عن
تاريخ خلنير، يسرنا أن نرحب بضيفنا مختار القرية، المختار زياد
محمد قوشو.
The people of the village came here more than 600 years ago.
To talk about the history of Khilneer, we are pleased to
welcome our guest, the village Mukhtar, Mukhtar Ziad
Mohammed Qosho.
الله يعطيك العافية يا عمي.
May God give you health, uncle.
أهلاً وسهلاً، شرفتمونا.
Welcome, you honor us.
الله يكرمك، خلينا نمشي هيك شوي. احكيلي هالقرية، أهلها من أين
أتوا، قد إيش عمرهم، مين هن؟
May God honor you. Let's walk a bit this way. Tell me about
this village, where did its people come from, how old is it,
who are they?
أهل القرية قديمة جداً بالآلاف السنين، بكونوا سكانها يسكنون
في المغر.
The village's people are very old, thousands of years, its
inhabitants used to live in caves.
ونحن هون غربيتنا قرية جويق، شماليتنا قرية جويق تبعد عنا شي
كيلومتر واحد نحن بيننا وبينهم.
And here to our west is the village of Jweik, to our north
is the village of Jweik, it is about one kilometer away
between us and them.
قرية خلنير اسمها، قسمها خلنير، أي المكان، معالم كبير قديماً
ما بنعرف من أيمت.
The village of Khilneer, its name, its part is Khilneer,
meaning the place, a great landmark from ancient times, we
don't know since when.
بس اسمها خلنير، أي العالم الكبير.
But its name is Khilneer, meaning the great scholar.
والبعض قال أنه خليل الفحل؟
And some said it's Khalil the Stallion?
إيوه خليل الفحل، هي بروحوا فيها.
Yes, Khalil the Stallion, they say that too.
المهم إنها قديمة بالآلاف السنين.
The important thing is it's ancient, thousands of years old.
طيب طيب.
Right, right.
الأهل الحاليين اللي سكنوا فيها حالياً، قد إيش صار لهم هون؟
The current people who live in it now, how long have they
been here?
ضلوا هون شي مية وخمسين بيت.
There are about 150 houses here.
لا، قد إيش صار لهم هون ساكنين؟
No, how long have they been living here?
صار لهم هون من زمان، ما بنعرف، من أيام المغر، من أيام
التلال.
They have been here for a long time, we don't know, since
the days of the caves, since the days of the hills.
مين هن؟
Who are they?
مين هن، أكراد.
Who are they? Kurds.
من أي عشيرة؟
From which tribe?
ما بنعرف عن عشيرتهم، هن أكراد قديماً سكنوا هون. وتم العالم
الكردي خلنير، من أيمت ما بنعرف، بالآلاف السنين.
We don't know about their tribe, they are Kurds who lived
here anciently. And the Kurdish scholar Khilneer remained,
since when we don't know, for thousands of years.
أعطيني أسماء العوائل اللي هون.
Give me the names of the families here.
العوائل اللي هون في چقلية، عائلة اسمها چقلية، تابعين لعشيرة
الچقلي.
The families here are Jaqliya, a family named Jaqliya,
belonging to the Jaqli tribe.
وفي بيت عبدو نعسو، أقدم منا. وفي بيت علكو كمان أقدم منا.
And there is the Abdo Naso family, older than us. And there
is the Alko family, also older than us.
وفي عائلات تانية نزلت هون من مية سنة، ميتين سنة، رحلوا
واستوطنوا بخلنير.
And there are other families that came down here 100 years,
200 years ago, they migrated and settled in Khilneer.
تموا القديمين هلق هون نحن بيت علكو، وبيت چقلي، وبيت عبدو
نعسو، هدول اللي بقوا لحد هلق ساكنين فيها.
The old ones remained here now, we are the Alko family, the
Jaqli family, and the Abdo Naso family, these are the ones
who remained living in it until now.
بما فيها عائلات صغيرة إجوا كمان استوطنوا بخلنير. وسكنوا
فيها، جوزوا ولادهم، بقوا هم موجودين حالياً.
Including small families that also came and settled in
Khilneer. And lived in it, married their children, they are
present now.
هلق أنا اللي فهمته إنه هون اللي إجا الأصلي لهون، اللي من
چقلي، هو علي باكير.
Now what I understood is that the original one who came
here, from Jaqli, is Ali Bakir.
إيوه علي باكير.
Yes, Ali Bakir.
علي باكير إجا علق مع ابن عمه، ضرب ابن عمه قتله.
Ali Bakir came, he got into a fight with his cousin, he hit
his cousin and killed him.
ببيسني.
In Besni.
بيسني وين صايرة؟
Where is Besni located?
بتركيا.
In Turkey.
بتركيا، صايرة قبل العهد العثماني، لأنه كانت الحدود مفتوحة.
وأجا سكن هون بهي المنطقة، جويق وچقلي وخلنير.
In Turkey, before the Ottoman era, because the borders were
open. And he came and lived here in this area, Jweik, Jaqli,
and Khilneer.
مين كان هون ساكن بهالمنطقة؟
Who was living here in this area?
هالمنطقة كان في عائلة حسنة أفندية، كانوا حاكمين المنطقة.
وبعدين إجا جدي علي باكير سكن هون بهالبيت هذا.
In this area, there was the Hassana Afandiya family, they
were ruling the area. And then my grandfather Ali Bakir came
and lived here in this house.
عمر، أسس، وتم شي مية، أكتر. المهم، بعده لحد هلق هون نحن
بعيلة وحدة بندب، عادات أخلاق واحدة بهالقرية.
He built, founded, and stayed for about 100 years, more.
Anyway, after him until now we are here as one family,
following one custom and ethics in this village.
هلق أنا اللي فهمته إنه هون في سبعة وأربعين مغارة. قبل ما
تجوا أنتو لهون.
Now what I understood is that there are 47 caves here.
Before you came here.
قبل ما نجي.
Before we came.
كان يسكنها الإنسان.
People used to live in them.
إيوه، حتى هلق شلون.
Yes, even now, you see.
وإلها أسماء مختلفة. شو هي هي الأسماء، متل إيش؟
And they have different names. What are these names, like
what?
أسماء، شو اسمه، مغارة قپشو، أي هون هي تحت منا هون. وفي مغارة
تانية، مغارة صالان.
Names, what is it called, Qapsho cave, meaning here, it is
below us here. And there is another cave, Salan cave.
في مغارات كمان غيرهن، سوسه. أسماء غريبة، هي ما بنعرف شو
بيعني أصلها.
There are other caves too, Soseh. Strange names, we don't
know what their origin means.
ما هي مرتبطة بهي القرية؟
They are not related to this village?
لا مو مرتبطة لا.
No, not related, no.
لكن لما أجو أهل القرية سكنوا فيها.
But when the people of the village came, they lived in them.
إيوه.
Yes.
طيب، هون كان في مي؟
Okay, was there water here?
مي ما في، كان ينابيع سطحية يجري مي لهالـ، وادي شو اسمه.
There was no water, there were surface springs running water
to this, what is the valley's name.
وادي تزبي، الوادي المقابلنا اسمه وادي تزبي.
Tezbi Valley, the valley opposite us is called Tezbi Valley.
طيب، هذا الوادي اللي نحن شايفينه نحن. اللي مبنية الضيعة على
سفحه الشمالي. شو اسمه هذا الوادي؟
Okay, this valley that we see. That the village is built on
its northern slope. What is this valley called?
هالوادي بيقولوا له وادي تزبي، گليي تزبي. إيوه، هي منطقة
بهالاسم هي، معروفة بهالاسم.
This valley they call it Tezbi Valley, Geliye Tezbi. Yes,
this area is with this name, known by this name.
طيب، اللي أجو لهون الأوائل، كانوا رعاة، تجار، إيش كانوا؟
Okay, the first ones who came here, were they shepherds,
merchants, what were they?
ما بنعرف عن العصر القديم، كانوا، أحراش كلياتهم، أحراش كانوا.
We don't know about the ancient era, they were, it was all
forests, they were forests.
ما كان عندهم غنم؟
Didn't they have sheep?
أكيد عندهم، لا غنم ما عندهم، ماعز أكيد كان عندهم.
Sure they have, no sheep they don't have, goats for sure
they had.
عندهم ماعز، لأنه أحراش، صح.
They had goats?
They had goats, because it's forests, right.
أحراش، إي صحيح. هلق إنت عم تقلي جويق بعيدة من هون شمالي واحد
كيلو.
Forests, yes true. Now you are telling me Jweik is far from
here, north, one kilo.
شي واحد كيلومتر، إيوه.
About one kilometer, yes.
واحد كيلومتر. في طريق زفت بينكم وبينهم؟
One kilometer. Is there an asphalt road between you and
them?
ما في، في طريق معبد بس مو زفت. صعب عليهم.
There isn't, there is a paved road but not asphalt. It's
difficult for them.
بقايا مقالع.
Remains of quarries.
أيوة.
Yes.
يعني أنتو الآن بحاجة لطريق تربطكم فيها.
Meaning you are now in need of a road that connects you to
it.
أكيد.
Sure.
هلق الطريق لعفرين، من جويق أقرب ولا من كفرشيل؟
Now the road to Afrin, is it closer from Jweik or from
Kfarsheel?
لا، من جويق أقرب.
No, from Jweik is closer.
أقرب.
Closer.
هي جويق، وهي كفرشيل بعد منا هونيك من غربي.
This is Jweik, and this is Kfarsheel after us there from the
west.
يعني من جويق أقرب لكم من كفرشيل.
Meaning from Jweik is closer to you than from Kfarsheel.
إيوه.
Yes.
نعم. هلق اليوم، يعني إيش هي العادات والتقاليد اللي هون؟
عادات وتقاليد الناس؟
Yes. Now today, meaning what are the customs and traditions
here? The customs and traditions of the people?
عادات وتقاليد بيحبوا بعضهم، بيحترموا بعضهم، وعايشين بسلام،
وبيحافظوا على بعض بشكل متين.
Customs and traditions, they love each other, respect each
other, live in peace, and protect each other strongly.
حلو.
Nice.
ما حدا بيدغل، بيدخل بالضيعة من أيام العثمانية وقبل العثمانية
ما حدا بيدخل لهون.
No one deceives, enters the village from the Ottoman days
and before the Ottoman days, no one enters here.
ليه؟
Why?
لحد إننا متكاتفين، محبين. ما بنحب المساوئ، لأنه منحب الحياة
بشكلها الطبيعي.
To the extent that we are united, loving. We don't like bad
things, because we love life in its natural form.
بس أنا سمعت إنه نقلاً عنك إنه أنتو عنيفين شوي.
But I heard quoting you, that you are a bit violent.
هي عنيفين أكيد، إنه طبيعة جبلية أكيد بده يكون عنيفين. لأنه
عايشين مع الوحوش، عايشين مع العصابات، أكيد بدنا نكون عنيفين.
That's violent for sure, being a mountainous nature for sure
they will be violent. Because living with wild animals,
living with gangs, for sure we need to be violent.
لا لا، مو عصابات، مو عصابات.
No no, not gangs, not gangs.
مو عصابات تبع هلق، عصابات قديمة.
Not today's gangs, old gangs.
إي قديمة. هلق أنتو مزاجكم شوي هيك قاسي.
Yes, old. Now your mood is a bit tough like this.
مزاجنا قاسي لأنه خاميين، فطريين.
Our mood is tough because we are raw, instinctive.
بتحبوا بسرعة، وبتعصبوا بسرعة، وبترجعوا بتصطلحوا بسرعة.
بتسامحوا بسرعة، مو هيك؟
You love quickly, get angry quickly, and reconcile quickly.
You forgive quickly, isn't it like that?
إيوه، إيوه. لأنه ما بنخلي شي بقلبنا، بنحكي كلمة، طاولك ليش
حكيت، بنحاسبه مباشرة من صفي القلوب.
Yes, yes. Because we don't keep anything in our hearts, we
say a word, right away why did you speak, we hold him
accountable directly, we clear the hearts.
ما بتشيلوا كتير بقلبكم.
You don't carry much in your hearts.
ما بنشيل شي بقلبنا.
We don't carry anything in our hearts.
كريمين؟
Generous?
كريمين، ما عندنا شي، بتحكي كلمة كويسة تاخد كل شي من عندنا.
Generous, we hold back nothing, you say a good word you take
everything from us.
بتحبوا الغريب؟
Do you like strangers?
بنحب الغريب، إي، غريب أديب، عندنا نحن بتحترمه.
We like strangers, yes, a polite stranger, we respect them.
أي قرية غيركم ما بعرف.
Any other village I don't know.
هون بيجي غريب، بنعطيه عيونا. كلهم كويسين، بس أي إنسان بيجي
لخلنير يجي غريب، نحن بنحترمه، إنه هذا غريب، بدنا نحترمه.
Here a stranger comes, we give him our eyes. All of them are
good, but any person who comes to Khilneer as a stranger, we
respect him, that this is a stranger, we must respect him.
ما شاء الله عليكم. الله يحييك.
God bless you. May God greet you.
Ya ahlan inşallah tkunu... Ya mît ahla.
May God keep you safe.
Welcome, I hope you are... A hundred welcomes.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health.
Ahlayn aamtî, Allah y'afîkî inşallah.
Welcome auntie, may God give you health, God willing.
As-salamu alaykum.
Peace be upon you.
Marhaba ya şebab.
And upon you be peace.
Hello, guys.
Şlonkon?
How are you?
Ya'tîkon al-aafiye.
Praise be to God.
May God give you health.
Şlonak? Hala hbbab.
How are you? Welcome, dear.
Min wen?
Where are you from?
Wallahî min al-Letamne, rîf Hema al-şemalî.
By God, from Al-Lataminah, the northern countryside of Hama.
Ya ahla wa sahla fîkon.
You are very welcome.
Ya mît ahla wa sahla.
A hundred welcomes.
Xellîna nwaqif la hon.
Let's stop right here.
Tayyib hek... Netfarraj min hon aal-day'a w nihkî ma'kon
şway.
Alright... Let's look at the village from here and talk to
you a bit.
Tfaddal.
Go ahead.
Nwaqif hon. Şlon hal-day'a?
We'll stand here. How is this village?
Wallahî alhamdulillah tamam.
By God, praise be to God, it's fine.
Şqad sarlkon hon?
How long have you been here?
Wallahî sarna hon şî sini w nos, sinten teqrîban.
By God, we've been here for a year and a half, almost two
years.
Êê.
Yeah.
Şu byeştiğil walidak?
What does your father do for a living?
Wallahî waldî hallaqten teqrîban aaxid ard...
By God, currently my father has rented a piece of land...
aind wahid ma'na min al-letamne ya'nî... am niştiğil bi hal
aradî.
With someone from Al-Lataminah who is with us... we are
working on these lands.
Hon taht aind al-Mahmoudiya, bi Efrîn, honîk.
Here?
Down here near Mahmoudiya, in Afrin, over there.
Intu şu am tiştiğlu fîha?
What are you doing there?
Nawatîr, ya'nî mantara.
Guarding, like a watchman.
Ah, am yentor natara huwî.
Ah, he is working as a watchman.
Êê.
Yes.
Intu tullab?
Are you students?
Na'am. Tasi', sinî...
Yes. Ninth grade, this year...
Axûy w uxtî, w ya'nî tlatî nihna xwat...
My brother and sister, we are three siblings...
Nihna erba'a. Ana sinî bacalorîya, w xwatî tlatî ncihu
alhamdulillah hal sinî bil tasi'.
We are four. I'm in my senior year of high school, and my
three siblings passed the ninth grade this year, praise be
to God.
Maşa'Allah, al-tlatî ncihu bil tasi'? Mabrouk!
Mashallah, all three passed the ninth grade?
Congratulations!
Hallaytu hon? Hallaytu la axûk w al-aa'île wala ma hallaytu
hon?
Did you give out sweets here? Did you give sweets for your
brother and family or not?
Hallaynahon.
We did.
Êş l-tihlaye kanit?
What kind of sweets was it?
Nouga w şarab.
Nougat and juice.
Sahten w aafîye! Ma lhiqnakon.
Bon appétit! We missed it.
Şlon anta hasis, ilmî wla adabî?
What about you, are you studying science or literature?
Ilmî wallah, alhamdulillah.
Science, by God, praise be to God.
Şlon hek fahasat kanit?
How were your exams?
Wallahî alhamdulillah, ana hal sinî beddî qaddim bacalorîya,
lissa ma qaddamtu.
By God, praise be to God, I am going to take my senior exams
this year, I haven't taken them yet.
Lissa ma qaddamt? Inna barkî iza mna'rif emta al-nata'ic
mnici mnihdarha.
You haven't taken them yet? We thought if we knew when the
results are out, we would come to attend.
Ahla wa sahla fîkon.
You are very welcome.
Allah yuhayîk.
May God greet you.
Allah ysallmak ya rab.
May God protect you.
Wayn am btudrusu hon, bil day'a?
Where are you studying here, in the village?
Wallahî am ninzil bil motor... aala Efrîn wallah.
By God, we go down by motorcycle... to Afrin, by God.
Rûha cayye... uxtî am btdawim bil aasr, w nihna mndawim al-
sobh...
Going and coming... my sister attends in the afternoon, and
we attend in the morning...
Ya'nî bidna nrouh şî maşwarîn aala Efrîn wallah.
So we have to make about two trips to Afrin, by God.
Kill yom?
Every day?
Allah ya'tîkon al-aafîye. Mesafit lî Efrîn 5 kîlo?
Every day.
May God give you strength. Is the distance to Afrin 5
kilometers?
Êê teqrîban.
Yes, approximately.
5 kîlo. Şlon wada' al-nas honîk?
5 kilometers. How is the people's situation there?
Wallahî aayşîn alhamdulillah, bistîqrar, tamam.
By God, they are living, praise be to God, in stability,
everything is fine.
Xedematkon şlon, m'ammanî? Mayy, kehreba, xubz?
How are your services, are they secured? Water, electricity,
bread?
Alhamdulillah wallah, carna hon Allah yu'tîh al-aafîye...
Praise be to God, our neighbor here, may God give him
health...
Am y'abbîlna mayy, mniştirî tarnazat mathalan, w bykett
by'abbîlna mayy.
He fills water for us, we buy tankers for example, and he
pours and fills water for us.
Ya'nî ahl al-day'a hadninekon, byhebbukon...
So the village people have embraced you, they love you...
Alhamdulillah, tamam.
Praise be to God, yes.
W antu cîran kwayysîn.
And you are good neighbors.
Alhamdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Allah ya'tîkon al-aafîye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk ya rab.
Şu malak? Allah ysallmak. Êş nawî tsîr anta?
What about you? May God protect you. What do you want to
become?
Mhamî.
A lawyer.
Mhamî! Ya selam. Laysh beddak tsîr mhamî?
A lawyer! Wow. Why do you want to be a lawyer?
Mşan aaxudh huquq al-nas.
So I can secure people's rights.
Huquq al-nas? Hilu! W anta?
People's rights? Beautiful! And you?
Wallahî nawî sîr mxaddir, taxdîr.
By God, I intend to become an anesthetist, anesthesia.
Tabîb taxdîr?
An anesthesiologist?
Taxdîr.
Anesthesia.
Laysh?
Why?
Wallahî hal mihne ana bhebba wallah.
By God, I love this profession.
Êê şu l-sirr bhebbak la tabîb al-taxdîr bizzat?
Yeah, what is the secret to you loving anesthesiology
specifically?
Wallahî min soğarî xalî bil taxdîr... min soğarî qallî
inşallah tatla'lî.
By God, since my childhood, my uncle is in anesthesia...
Since my childhood, he told me, God willing, you'll turn out
like me.
Ya selam. Ma'natha anta mu'cab bi xalak.
Wow. That means you admire your uncle.
Na'am.
Yes.
Allah yqawwîkon. Inşallah mnşufkon tabîb taxdîr w mhamî
nacih.
May God give you strength. God willing, we will see you as
an anesthesiologist and a successful lawyer.
Wa ana mhamî.
God willing.
And I am a lawyer.
As-salamu alaykum.
God willing.
Peace be upon you.
Allah ysallmak ya rab. Ahla.
May God protect you. Welcome.
[Music]
As-salamu alaykum.
Peace be upon you.
Maşa'Allah al-baraka l-hilwe. Şlonak?
Mashallah, what a beautiful blessing. How are you?
Alhamdulillah aal-salame.
Welcome, sir.
Thank God for your safety.
Ya ahla wa sahla. Marhaba aammo.
Welcome, a hundred welcomes.
You are very welcome. Hello, uncle.
Ahlayn w sahlayn ya ustad. Ya ahla wa sahla.
Welcome, sir. You are very welcome.
Marhaba ya haccî. Şlonkî?
Hello, Hajji. How are you?
Alhamdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Ismahouli abrik ma'kon şway?
Allow me to sit with you for a bit?
Şeref! Ya ahlan wa sahlan wa marhaba! Mîyat ahla wa sahlan!
It's an honor! You are welcome and hello! A hundred
welcomes!
Allah ysallimkon. Şlonak aammo?
May God protect you. How are you, uncle?
Alhamdulillah, da'yînlak. Alhamdulillah, maşî l-hal. Kayfîn
alhamdulillah.
Praise be to God, praying for you. Praise be to God, things
are fine. We are doing well, praise be to God.
Alhamdulillah. Aarrifnî aalayk.
Praise be to God. Introduce yourself to me.
Ahlan, ismî Subhî Mustafa.
Welcome, my name is Subhi Mustafa.
Ya ahla wa sahla fîk.
You are very welcome.
Allah ysallmak ya xûy, Allah yuwaffiqak.
May God protect you, my brother, may God grant you success.
Qaddeş aamrak?
How old are you?
Aamrî... hawaley tmanîn.
My age... around eighty.
Maşa'Allah.
Mashallah.
Tmanîn, wahid wa tmanîn teqrîban. Daxil bil wahid wa tmanîn.
Eighty, almost eighty-one. Entering my eighty-first year.
Al-aamer killo inşallah.
May you live a long life, God willing.
Al-haccî, al-haccî zawictak?
And the Hajji, is she your wife?
Êê wallah kaman aamra hek haa, teqrîban.
Yes, by God, her age is around the same, approximately.
Ya haccî... Tellî'î aalayna şway. Hkî ma'î.
Oh, Hajji... Look at us a bit. Talk to me.
Ez nizanib bi erebî.
I don't know Arabic.
Ma bta'rif taxkî arabî.
She doesn't know how to speak Arabic.
Twarrattî?
Did you get stuck?
Ma bta'rif arabî.
She doesn't know Arabic.
Ana ma ba'rif arabî kitî.
I don't know Arabic much.
Al-hadratak abno?
Are you her son?
Maşa'Allah.
Yes, by God.
Mashallah.
Ismak al-karîm, ant al-kabîr?
Yes, my son!
Your noble name, are you the eldest?
Ahmed... Ahmed Subhî Mustafa.
Ahmad... Ahmad Subhi Mustafa.
Ya ahla wa sahla fîk.
You are very welcome.
Ya hala. Ya hala.
Welcome. Welcome.
W l-ax?
And the brother?
Xalid Mustafa.
Khalid Mustafa.
Ahla wa sahla. Şu btîqrabu la l-haccî?
Welcome. How are you related to the Hajji?
Bîkon ibn xalî, xalî huwî.
I'm his nephew, he is my uncle.
L-mara bitkun aammitna... aammitî...
The woman is our aunt... my aunt...
Ahla wa sahla fîkon.
You are all very welcome.
Biddî as'alak aan hal day'a l-hilwî.
I want to ask you about this beautiful village.
Ya ahlan wa sahlan fîkon.
You are very welcome.
Allah yekrimak. Hkîlî aanna. Şlon ziraa'îta, şlon nasa, şlon
ahla?
May God honor you. Tell me about it. How is its agriculture,
how are its people, how are its residents?
Ya axî... awwal... awwal zira'a la awwalî...
My brother... first... agriculture in the past...
Nizra' hinta, şa'îr, aadas...
We used to plant wheat, barley, lentils...
Êêwa. W ba'dayn... bil mancal... n-hawwiş al-hinta.
Yes. And then... with a sickle... we would harvest the
wheat.
Awwal şî kan hassa... ma fî kan hassa...
At first, it was harvesting... there was no harvester...
Hasad aal mancal?
Harvesting with a sickle?
Êêwa, bil mancal awwalî.
Yes, with the sickle in the past.
Ba'd al-mancal, fî tratorat ma fî.
After the sickle, there were no tractors.
Bil bağal... ninjîbo aal baydar. Nînadruso...
With a mule... we would bring it to the threshing floor. We
would thresh it...
Fî asmo... haylan... haylan bil arabî?
There was something called... haylan... haylan in Arabic?
Haylîn.
Haylin.
Haylîn?
Haylin?
Haylîn ma ba'rif in şu.
Haylin, I don't know what it is.
Hawwa.
Threshing board.
Êê. W bil bağal kaza aam...
Yes. And with the mule, like that...
B-tor... baqar ya'nî fallaha, kan awwal hek.
With a bull... meaning an ox for plowing, that's how it was
in the past.
Na'am.
Yes.
W la... alhamdulillah hallaq m-dinya ttawawarît. Al-dinya
saret alf xayr alhamdulillah.
But no... praise be to God, now the world has developed. The
world has become a thousand times better, praise be to God.
Ya axî ya'nî zman awwalî kan hek.
My brother, in the old times, it was like that.
Kan fî aandkon trabbu... ğanam, maa'iz, kaza hek? Abqar?
Did you used to raise... sheep, goats, things like that?
Cows?
Êê ğ-... lakan! Hayy muğara kan...
Yes, sheep... of course! This cave here...
Kan malyan 50 ras ğanam. W baqar, tlatî baqar.
It was full of 50 heads of sheep. And cows, three cows.
Kan aandî, wa aandî bağal taba' faddan.
I had them, and I had a mule for plowing.
Hon bil muğara kan aandî...
Here in the cave I had...
fî mahal taba' tibin, fî mahal taba' ğanam, maa'iz. Wasi'
mahalla.
A place for straw, a place for sheep, goats. Its space is
wide.
Wasi'. Anta aala zmanak tam taşcîr al-cabal bil zaytun, wala
qabl kan zaytun mawcûd?
Wide. During your time, was the mountain planted with olive
trees, or were olives there before?
Wala awwalî zaytun ma fî.
By God, there were no olives in the past.
Aala zmanak saccartu?
You planted them during your time?
Êêwa ma fî. L-ard killo kan bour.
Yes, there were none. The whole land was barren.
Ba'dayn al-aalam zara'at.
Then people planted.
Ttawwarît... al-zaytun, zaytun cedîd, kill al-aalam ba'dayn
zara'it zaytun.
It developed... olives, new olives, then everyone planted
olives.
Na'am. Na'am.
Yes. Yes.
Êêwa.
Yes.
As'alak aan al-zaytun. Anta ibno lal haccî, akîd aamrak...
50, şqad aamrak?
Let me ask you about the olives. You are the Hajji's son,
surely your age is... 50, how old are you?
Êê 50, foq al-xamsîn lissa, sittî w xamsîn sinî.
Yes 50, over fifty still, fifty-six years old.
Foq al-xamsîn. Al-aamer killo inşallah.
Over fifty. A long life to you, God willing.
Ahlan.
Welcome.
Hkîlî aan zaytun hon.
Tell me about the olives here.
Wallah zaytun kan awwalî... ma fî ya'nî intac ma fî.
By God, the olives in the past... there wasn't, meaning
there wasn't production.
Bass sar kam sinî, kill şacara çuwal, çuwal...
But a few years ago, every tree yields a sack, a sack...
Çuwal w cubal btutla' çuwal tanaktayn.
A sack, and in the mountains it yields a sack and two
jerrycans (of oil).
Qasdak al-zaytun bil cabal byitla' tanaktayn?
You mean the olives in the mountain yield two jerrycans?
Êê min daşit... tanake.
Yes, in the plains... one jerrycan.
Bi-sahel tanake?
In the plains, one jerrycan?
Êê sahel.
Yes, plains.
Êê.
Yes.
Mu ard hamra, u mu intac ya'nî mu mitl cabal. Cabal ard
abyad w btutla' zayt ya'nî aala...
It's not red soil, and the production is not like the
mountains. The mountain has white soil and yields more
oil...
Ya'nî hon zaytun kwayyis?
Meaning the olives here are good?
Êê.
Yes.
Êşu no'o?
What type is it?
Zaytun aadi. Taba' şokî, mitl... mu mitl l-niğnî hallaq
b-zra'o.
Regular olives. The thorny type, like... not like the ones
they plant now.
Ya'nî xalxalî, zayyatî, êş no'o?
Meaning Khalkhali, Zayyati, what type?
Êê b-zra'o mu mitl zayyatî.
Yes, what they plant is not like Zayyati.
Lal bay', l-tacir, l-m'asara btkeddu aala zayt, êş bi-sawî
al-aalam?
Is it for selling, for the merchant, do you press it for oil
at the press, what do people do?
L-m'asara nihna ma... ma... t-tuccar ma byiştaru. Bass
m-sakkî...
The press, we don't... the merchants don't buy it. We just
store it...
Mşan... z-...
For provisions?
For...
Êşu fî aandkon ğayr al-zaytun zira'a?
What other crops do you have besides olives?
Rumman. Rumman, summaq, şağlat hek ya'nî.
Pomegranates. Pomegranates, sumac, things like that.
Ya'nî l-rumman fîna n-a'tabro zira'a asasîyye l-nas aayşe
aalayha?
So can we consider pomegranates a primary crop that people
live on?
Ii lakan!
Yes, of course!
Fî rumman kwayyis hon?
Is there good pomegranate here?
Rumman kbar w m-tallî'a...
Big pomegranates, and they yield well...
Haccî fî aandkon hon kanit ya'nî uyun mayy şî? Carîye wala
la? Abar, killha abar?
Hajji, did you have any water springs here? Flowing or not?
Wells, are they all wells?
Wallah aamrî sar 80 sinî, ma şift l-mayy carîye.
By God, I'm 80 years old now, I've never seen flowing water.
Hon mantiqatna hon ma fî carîye kan.
In our area here, there was no flowing water.
Abadan. Fî bîr... atharî.
Never. There is an ancient... well.
Bîr arabî qadîm, atharî.
An old Arab well, ancient.
Êê. Qadîm. Qadîm hatha.
Yes. Old. That is old.
Kan fî mayytu mitl bouz.
Its water was like ice.
Tişrabu minnu.
You used to drink from it.
Barid, êêwa lakan! L-day'a killa aam tişrab minnu.
Cold, yes of course! The whole village used to drink from
it.
W t-saqqî l-haywanat minnu?
And water the animals from it?
Ii lakan. La, haywan aal cîb hazîk...
Yes, of course. No, the animals from that well...
Illo cabbayn hon. Wahid lal ğanam, lal ma'iz, lal baqar, lal
dawwab...
It has two wells here. One for the sheep, the goats, the
cows, the beasts...
W wahid l-şirib, hon l-day'a. Hazîk...
And one for drinking, here for the village. That one...
Hallaq hallaq min ayn am tişrabu mayy?
Right now, where do you drink water from?
Min cîb şo asmo... Hallaq am tişrabu mayy min c-cîb?
From a well, what's it called... Are you drinking water from
the well now?
Irtîwazî.
Artesian.
Irtîwazî. Êê irtîwazî. Kil day'a c-cîb... irtîwazî.
Artesian. Yes, artesian. The whole village's well...
artesian.
Wa hazak qadîme killo sakkaro.
And that old one, they completely closed it.
Sakkaro. Hkîlî aan halet l-nas honî. Şlon wada' l-nas hon?
They closed it. Tell me about the condition of the people
here. How is the situation of the people here?
Alhamdulillah. Halet l-nas kwayyse. Hallaq min qabil ma kan
kwayyse. Hallaq alhamdulillah saret kwayyse ya'nî.
Praise be to God. The people's condition is good. Now,
before it wasn't good. Now, praise be to God, it has become
good.
Ballaşat l-şacarat l-zaytun, saret tintic, yitla' mawsam.
Ya'nî saret ahwal madîyye kwayyse.
The olive trees started, they started producing, there's a
harvest. Meaning the financial situations became good.
Wada' l-nas l-mutawassit, ya'nî l-umoum l-nas hnne fuqara...
The average people's situation, meaning are the majority of
people poor...
Wala mutawassitîn, wala halon mnîha... saraha?
Or middle-class, or is their condition good... honestly?
La, bi-hal day'a ma fî hada ya'nî ktîr umouro mnîha, li'anno
mantiqa cabalîyye...
No, in this village there isn't anyone whose situation is
very good, because it's a mountainous area...
Ya'nî mawasim mu ktîr... mu mitl hal sahel...
Meaning the harvests aren't a lot... not like the plains...
Alhamdulillah, masturîn alhamdulillah, aala kill hal.
Praise be to God, they get by, praise be to God, in any
case.
Ya'nî l-umoum l-nas wasat w ma doun.
So generally, people are middle-class or below.
Wasat. Wasat w bi-couz aqall min wasat kaman.
Middle. Middle, and maybe even less than middle as well.
Tamam. Allah yuqawwîkon ya rab.
Alright. May God give you strength.
Biddî as'al l-haccî bass.
I just want to ask the Hajji.
Êê ya haccî, tawwalî balek aalayya şway bass!
Yes?
Yes Hajji, just bear with me for a bit!
Wala... ma b'arif... ma ba'rif arabî...
By God... I don't know... I don't know Arabic...
Al-haccî am y-qullî inno intî kintî tğannî...
The Hajji is telling me that you used to sing...
Ya'nî bil kurdî!
Meaning in Kurdish!
[Laughs] Tğannî? La, wa-llah, la.
[Laughs] Sing? No, by God, no.
T-haqqaqîlî aan awladîk, aindîk kam walad? Allah y-xallîhon.
Tell me about your children, how many children do you have?
May God protect them.
Na'am?
Yes?
Thlathî?
Three?
Thlathî.
Three.
Allah y-xallîhon. Şebab?
May God protect them. Boys?
W banat?
Yes.
And girls?
Banat... xamse.
Girls... five.
Allah y-xallîhon ya rab.
May God protect them.
Hawaletek killon?
Are they all around you?
Wala abadan ma b-ğannî la dawla. [laughing]
By God, I never sing for the state. [laughing]
Ma b-ğannî... m-hayyatî... xwedê, di jiyana xwe de min
negotiye.
I don't sing... in my life... By God, I haven't sung in my
life.
Şlon awwalî kintî... ma kintî trouhî aal a'ras?
How was it before... didn't you go to weddings?
La la... nizarim bikim... la b-rquz w la b-ğannî.
No, no... I don't know how to do it... I neither dance nor
sing.
Laysh?
Why?
Hek.
Just because.
Yom aros ma ğanaytî?
On your wedding day, you didn't sing?
Yom aros ibnkî?
No.
On your son's wedding day?
Aros ibnik?
Your son's wedding?
La. Wa-lla, wa-lla ma ğanaytu.
No. By God, by God I didn't sing.
Allah y'atîkon al-aafîye. Ktîr inbasatna.
May God give you health. We enjoyed it very much.
Allah y'atîkon al-aafîye. Inşallah mnşufkon hek awladkon...
wa ahfadkon w btunbustu.
May God give you health. God willing, we will see you like
this with your children... and your grandchildren, and
you'll be happy.
Şukran, Allah ya'tîk, taslamu, taslamu.
Thank you, may God give you, bless you, bless you.
Allah y'tîkon al-aafîye.
May God give you health.
Allah yqawwîkon, Allah yqawwîkon.
May God give you strength, may God give you strength.
Allah ysallmak.
May God protect you.
احسن من أولي، الحمد لله والشكر.
Better than before, praise and thanks be to God.
الحمد لله، الحمد لله، الحمد لله.
Praise be to God, praise be to God, praise be to God.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And upon you be peace and the mercy of God.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
شفتك هلق فوق.
May God give you health, welcome.
I saw you up there just now.
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
عند الحجي.
At the Hajj's place.
بس قالوا إنه في معصرة؟
Yes.
But they said there is a press?
في معصرة، معصرة قديمة هون، شفتها؟
There is a press, an old press here, did you see it?
إيش وضع هالمعصرة هي؟
What is the situation with this press?
هاي معصرة بيطلع شي ١٥٠ عمرها.
This press is about 150 years old.
١٥٠ سنة؟
150 years?
تفضل.
150 years, yes.
Please go ahead.
تفضل.
Please.
بس وكأنه البناء تبعها جديد؟
But it seems its building is new?
بناء جديد بس المعصرة الآلات القديمة هون.
The building is new, but the press machines are old here.
اشرحلي.
Explain to me.
خلي بس الكاميرا تشوف الضوء.
Let the camera just see the light.
إيه، هون إيشو هون؟
Yes, what is here?
هون بينزلوا زيتون من هون.
Here they drop the olives from here.
إيوا.
I see.
بيحطوا من شوالات بينزلوا من هون.
They put them from sacks, they drop them from here.
هاي حلزون.
This is a spiral.
إيوا.
I see.
بيجيبها لهون عالطحانة.
It brings them here to the grinder.
اسمه حجر، بالكردي بيقولوا حجر هي طحانة.
It's called a stone, in Kurdish they say 'hacer', this is a
grinder.
عجانة يعني بيعجنها بتطحنها.
A kneader, I mean it kneads it and grinds it.
هي كانت أولي يسحبوها الخيول؟
Was this originally pulled by horses?
أولي كان خيول.
Originally it was horses.
بس هلق صارت هاي عالكهربا هاي.
But now this has become electric.
عالموتور على المولدة بتشتغل.
It works on a motor, on a generator.
إيوا، عمرها؟
I see, its age?
عمرها تقريبا شي يعني ١٥٠ سنة.
Its age is roughly, I mean, 150 years.
١٥٠ سنة.
150 years.
إيه.
Yes.
بتيجي من هون...
It comes from here...
العجين بتطلع بتيجي من هون.
I see.
The dough comes out, it comes from here.
من شو اسمه... من الحجر بتنزل لهون.
From what's it called... from the stone it goes down to
here.
نعم.
Yes.
وفي هون طاولة بيحطوا بين العليقات هون.
And there is a table here, they put it between the bags
here.
ومن عليق بيحطوا عالشادة.
And from the bag they put it on the presser.
عالشادة.
On the presser.
عالمكبس يعني.
On the press, I mean.
الشادة هي بتعصر البيرين بتطالع الزيت.
The presser, it presses the pomace to extract the oil.
أولي كان يدوي، بيبرموا على اليدوي.
Originally it was manual, they would turn it manually.
مم.
Mm.
مسنن، يعني شرار كان...
Toothed, I mean a gear was...
هلق صار بيسطون.
Now it has become a piston.
يعني محدثينها.
So they modernized it.
إيه بيسطون.
Yes, a piston.
بينزل زيت من هون من الشادة وبينزل على هال... جوار.
Oil comes down from here from the presser and goes down to
these... wells.
عالجوار.
To the wells.
من جوار هدول الجوار.
From the wells, these wells.
كان في هون فرازة، هلق مفرطينها.
There used to be a separator here, now they have taken it
apart.
بتطلع زيت صافي من الفرازة وبتنحط بالتنكات.
Pure oil comes out of the separator and is put into tins.
تمام.
Perfect.
هلق شقد صار لها هالمعصرة واقفة؟
Now, how long has this press been stopped?
هاي صار لها تقريبا شي ١٠ سنين واقفة.
This has been stopped for about 10 years.
١٠ سنين.
10 years.
إيه من ١٠ سنين وكان عم يشتغلوا.
Yes, since 10 years ago, and they were working.
بس مو هلق صار كله معاصر الحديثة ما عاد يستفيد يعني.
But now that there are all modern presses, it is no longer
profitable.
معناته هاي المعصرة كانت تعصر لخلنير والضيع الحواليها.
So this press used to press for Xelnir and the surrounding
villages.
إي نعم.
Yes indeed.
مزبوط؟
Right?
كان عم يعصروا إيه.
They used to press, yes.
كانت في مغارة سابقا هي؟
Was this a cave previously?
هي لا هاي بناء جديدة.
This one no, this is a new building.
لا قصدي هي المعصرة ما كانت في مغارة؟
No, I mean this press wasn't in a cave?
لا هون لا.
No, not here.
هونيك بالضيعة كان في مغارة، في كان فيها معصرة من قديم.
There in the village there was a cave, there was a press in
it from old times.
معصرة قديمة.
An old press.
معصرة قديمة إيه.
An old press, yes.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك مية سلامة، أهلين فيكم، أهليين فيكم.
May God give you health, a hundred welcomes, welcome to you,
welcome to you.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
أزاد إيش؟
Azad what?
أزاد فريد مصطفى.
Azad Farid Mustafa.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
وإنت؟
And you?
روني.
Roni.
روني؟ لك أهلاً وسهلاً يا روني.
Roni? Well welcome Roni.
هالوردات لمين؟
Who are these flowers for?
لإلك.
For you.
لإلي؟
For me?
ورد وشايل ورد، وين كنتوا هيك؟
Oh wow.
A flower carrying flowers, where were you like this?
هون بالضيعة.
Here in the village.
ضيعة؟ ضيعة حلوة.
The village? A beautiful village.
إيش عم تدرس إنت؟
Yes.
What are you studying?
عم تدرس إنت بالمدرسة؟
Are you studying at school?
أي صف؟
Which grade?
رابع.
Fourth.
وروني؟
And Roni?
أول.
First.
إنت صرت أول؟
You are in first grade?
أكيد إنت الأولى.
Surely you are the first.
مزبوط؟
Right?
إنت مو أولى؟
Aren't you first?
أولى!
No.
First!
أزاد قال لي أولى.
Azad told me first.
إيه.
Yes.
إنت أي درجة؟
What grade are you?
درجة...
Grade...
عشرة.
Ten.
عشرة! لا.
Ten! No.
إيه، احكي لنا لنشوف هلق.
Yes, tell us let's see now.
إيش حبيت بهال... ورجيني إياها لشوف؟
What did you like about this... show it to me let's see?
شممني إياها لشوف.
Let me smell it let's see.
الله! كتير كتير حلو.
God! Very very beautiful.
هدا من بيتكم؟
Is this from your house?
بيتكم هاد الورد؟
Yes.
Your house has this flower?
إيش هاد حاطته على راسك؟
What is this you put on your head?
قشطة.
A hair tie.
قشطة! يا سلام.
A hair tie! Oh wow.
إيش بتحب بهالضيعة إنت يا أزاد؟
What do you like in this village, Azad?
إيشو فيها الضيعة حلو، إيش بتحب بضيعتك إنت؟
What is beautiful in the village, what do you like in your
village?
إنت من خلينر مو من خلينر؟
You are from Xelnir, right?
إيه.
Yes.
إيش بتحبوا بالضيعة؟
What do you like in the village?
إيشو بالضيعة فيها شي حلو احكي لي لشوف؟
What does the village have that's beautiful, tell me let's
see?
أكتر شي بتحبه؟
The thing you like the most?
وردات.
Flowers.
أهل خلينر.
The people of Xelnir.
أهل خلينر حلو.
The people of Xelnir, nice.
إيش بتحب فيهم؟ إيش فيهم حلو؟
What do you like about them? What is nice about them?
قل لي شو الشي الحلو بأهل خلينر؟
Tell me what is the nice thing about the people of Xelnir?
خلينا نمشي شوي.
Let's walk a little.
كل شي.
Everything.
طيبين؟
Are they kind?
طيبين.
Kind.
طيبين، بيحبوا بعض؟
Kind, do they love each other?
بيحبوا الغريب؟
Do they love the stranger?
إيه.
Yes.
إيش بدك تصير بالمستقبل؟
What do you want to be in the future?
ها؟
Huh?
إيش بدك تصير بالمستقبل؟
What do you want to be in the future?
حلاق.
A barber.
ليش حلاق؟
Why a barber?
ها؟
Huh?
ليش بدك تصير حلاق؟
Why do you want to be a barber?
بدي أشتغل حلاق.
I want to work as a barber.
بتحب تشتغل حلاق؟
You love working as a barber?
مين قاصص لك هالشعرات هيك؟
Who cut your hair like this?
حلاق.
A barber.
حلاق هون بالضيعة؟
A barber here in the village?
لا بعفرين.
No, in Afrin.
لكا؟ عفرين.
Oh? Afrin.
الله يقويك يا أزاد.
May God give you strength, Azad.
إن شاء الله هيك بنشوفك بالمستقبل متل ما بتحب تكون.
God willing, we will see you in the future as you like to
be.
وروني، شو بدك تصيري إنت يا روني؟
And Roni, what do you want to be, Roni?
إيش بدك تصيري بالمستقبل يا روني؟
What do you want to be in the future, Roni?
إيشو؟
What?
مهندسة زراعية مشان الورد.
An agricultural engineer for the flowers.
مزبوط؟
Right?
إيه.
Yes.
يلا الله يقويكم، الله يعافيكم.
Alright, may God give you strength, may God give you health.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of God and His
blessings.
شلونك أخ يوسف؟
How are you, brother Yusef?
أهليين وسهلين أستاذ مصطفى.
Welcome, Mr. Mustafa.
شرفتنا.
You honored us.
يا هلا يا هلا بسم الله تفضلوا.
Welcome, welcome, in the name of God, come in.
يوسف خلينيري واحد من شباب خلينر...
Yusef Xelniri, one of the young men of Xelnir...
اللي حرفيين والمهنيين، الذواق اللي بيحب هيك يشتغل...
Who are craftsmen and professionals, a man of taste who
likes to work like this...
بالخشب يعني إذا بدنا نسميه.
With wood, I mean, if we want to call it that.
يعني بيستعمل الوسائل الطبيعية.
I mean, he uses natural materials.
الزيتون، جذوع التفاح وبيساوي منهم أمازك.
Olive wood, apple tree trunks, and he makes emzeks from
them.
وبيساوي منهم الجوز.
And he makes walnuts from them.
وبيصنع يعني تحف ولعب وأشياء كلياتها نفاضة.
And he manufactures, I mean, antiques, toys, and things that
are all ashtrays.
كلها أشياء يعني بتناسب البيوت يعني أشياء فنية.
All things, I mean, that suit homes, I mean artistic things.
احكي لي شوي هيك عن شغفك بهالأشياء أخ يوسف؟
Tell me a little about your passion for these things,
brother Yusef?
والله هي المهنة يعني...
Well, this profession, I mean...
كـ من عندي يعني اطلعت عليها إنها مهنة كويسة يعني.
As coming from me, I mean, I looked at it as a good
profession, I mean.
بحرف هي الشغلة.
I craft this thing.
وبلشت بالـ شو اسمه يعني مناظر صغار.
And I started with the, what's it called, I mean small
sceneries.
متل بيقولوا له بالعربي المشرب.
Like they call it in Arabic, the mashrab.
مشرب الدخان.
The smoking pipe.
بالكردي اسمه أمزك.
In Kurdish, it's called an emzek.
بلشنا فيهم وحطينا شوية مناظر.
Yes.
We started with them and put in some sceneries.
متلاً متل بزق، بزق كردي هدا.
For example, like a buzuq, this is a Kurdish buzuq.
إيوا.
I see.
شلون بتميزه إنه هاد بزق كردي؟
How do you distinguish that this is a Kurdish buzuq?
من البزق التركي مثلا أو...
From the Turkish buzuq for example, or...
يعني هو معروف بالكردي والتركي، عرفت شلون.
I mean, it's known in Kurdish and Turkish, you know what I
mean.
للعربي عود عندهم.
For the Arabs, they have the oud.
بيصير عود.
It becomes an oud.
لا، العود يعني طرب عربي.
No, the oud, I mean, is Arabic music.
بس الكردي معروف بالبزق والتركي.
But the Kurdish is known for the buzuq, and the Turkish.
تمام.
Perfect.
هدول هنن.
These are them.
والأمزكات هدول مثلا...
And these emzeks for example...
يعني واحد بيشتهي مثلا هيك منظر...
I mean, someone might desire, for example, such a scenery...
مو شرط إنه تشرب، يعني واحد بيحطه منظر عنده بالبيت كذا.
It's not a condition to smoke from it, I mean, one puts it
as a decoration at home and so on.
وبنشتغل فيهم.
And we work on them.
غير شي إيش بتشتغل؟
What else do you work on?
والله فينا نشتغل متل هدول اشتغلت فيهم مناظر كشكل فراشة.
Well, we can work like these, I worked on them as sceneries
in the shape of a butterfly.
ويعني تماثيل فيني أزبط.
And I mean, statues, I can make.
من النحت شو بيقولوا له؟
From carving, what do they call it?
نحت إيوا ومن الخشب كمان حفر.
Carving, exactly, and from wood as well, engraving.
حفر عالخشب.
Engraving on wood.
بحفر عالخشب كمان.
I engrave on wood too.
بترسم؟
Do you draw?
عندي هواية رسم كمان.
I have a drawing hobby too.
إيش ترسم؟
What do you draw?
والله مناظر طبيعية، إيش ما كان.
Well, natural sceneries, whatever it is.
هلق إنت عايش في الطبيعة، بيتكم هون يعني صاير بالجهة الشرقية
الجنوبية من...
Now you live in nature, your house here is, I mean, located
on the southeastern side of...
من الضيعة مظبوط.
Of the village, right.
إيوا، وبالتالي إنت عايش في الطبيعة، هي عم تلهمك؟
I see, and therefore you live in nature, is it inspiring
you?
هي الطبيعة بتسحبك، إنه كـ...
Nature pulls you, it as a...
يعني شلون بدي أقلك، بيعطيك إحساس إنه تشتغل بهالشي.
I mean, how can I say it, it gives you a feeling to work on
this thing.
يا سلام.
Oh wow.
عرفت شلون، يعني بتطلع حواليك جبال ومناظر كويسة.
You know what I mean, I mean you look around you at
mountains and beautiful sceneries.
متل الغروب أو كذا مثلا، غروب الشمس.
Like the sunset or such for example, the sunset.
يعني تطلع حواليك وخاصة مقابلنا عفرين مثلا، سهر عفرين، وقرية
كفرشيل وكذا مثلا.
I mean you look around you, and especially opposite us is
Afrin for example, the plain of Afrin, and the village of
Kafr Shil and so on for example.
يعني منظر كويس.
I mean, it's a beautiful scenery.
بتعطيك إلهام.
It gives you inspiration.
إيوا إلهام، يعني ما بتحب إنه الحياة هالمناظر إنه تفوتك عرفت
شلون.
Yes, inspiration, I mean you don't like for life and these
sceneries to pass you by, you know what I mean.
مثلا تحب تكون عطول حلم فيه.
For example, you like to always be dreaming of it.
تمام، تمام.
Perfect, perfect.
العدة اللي بتشتغل فيها إيش هي؟
The tools you work with, what are they?
العدة مجرد هالموس.
The tools are just this knife.
الموس صغير.
A small knife.
وبعدين مثلا بعد ما نخلص من الديكور...
And then for example, after we finish with the decoration...
بنحفه بالورق زيز...
We sand it with sandpaper...
بنزبطه، وثقب، عندي هاي يعني أدوات كلها ما في كهربا.
We fix it, and a drill, I have this, I mean tools that are
all without electricity.
أدوات يدوية يعني.
Manual tools, I mean.
يدوية كلها يدوية.
Manual, all manual.
كلها يدوية.
All manual.
كلها يدوية، وبنبلش بنـ مثلا بنفتل فيها مثلا، بس مشان شو إنه
بوجل الـ شو اسمه...
All manual, and we start to, for example, we turn it for
example, just so that, so that it smoothens the, what's it
called...
وبعدين بنزبطه...
And then we fix it...
وآخر شي...
And finally...
بعد ما خلصنا مثلا...
After we are done for example...
يعني من هالشكل هادا...
I mean, from this shape...
بنحط السكوتين عليه...
We put the varnish on it...
أو مثلا بيقولوا له لكر.
Or for example they call it lacquer.
بنزبطه و... بيطلع منظر حلو.
We fix it and... a beautiful look comes out.
ومجرب واحدة قدامك كمان إذا بدك.
And I can try one in front of you too if you want.
حاولت تشتغل شي بالتجارة، يعني تشتغل شي تجاري؟
Have you tried to work something in commerce, I mean, do
commercial work?
لا تجاري لا.
No, commercial no.
فقط هيك مزاج.
Just as a mood like this.
مزاج مزاج، إنه مو مشان المصلحة أو مثلا بالتجارة أو كذا.
A mood, a mood, it's not for business or for example in
commerce or such.
إنه هيك واحد مثلا، واحد بيجي لعند صاحبك مثلا، واحد بده شغلة
هدية...
It's just that, for example, someone comes to your friend
for example, someone wants a thing as a gift...
بتعطيه إياها مثلا بتتم عنده ذكرى.
You give it to him for example, it stays with him as a
memory.
عرفت شلون.
You know what I mean.
الله يعطيك العافية أخ يوسف.
May God give you health, brother Yusef.
الله يعافيك أهلاً وسهلاً شرفتم والله.
May God give you health, welcome, you have honored us by
God.
بالتوفيق إن شاء الله، هيك بنشوف عندك لوحات وبنشوف عندك يعني
أشياء هيك منحوتات.
Good luck God willing, so that we see you have paintings and
we see you have, I mean, things like sculptures.
إن شاء الله هيك بتشارك فيهم في معارض بإذن الله.
God willing, so that you participate with them in
exhibitions, God willing.
إن شاء الله مية السلامة وتشرفنا.
God willing, a hundred welcomes and we are honored.
الله يكرمك يا رب، أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God honor you, oh Lord, welcome.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
طبيعة خلينر الحلوة الجبلية اللي فيها وديان وفيها العديد من
أنواع الأشجار المثمرة وغير المثمرة والزهور...
The beautiful mountainous nature of Xelnir, which has
valleys and has many types of fruitful and non-fruitful
trees and flowers...
بتعطي الإنسان إلهام كتير حلو.
Gives a person a very beautiful inspiration.
فبيحب الرسم وبيحب النحت وأيضا بيحب الموسيقى.
So he loves drawing, and he loves carving, and also he loves
music.
وأهل خلينر بطبيعتهم ناس محافظين على التراث والعادات
والفلكلور.
And the people of Xelnir, by their nature, are a people who
preserve heritage, customs, and folklore.
شكري اللي الآن شايفينه خلفي، عم يعزف هلق عالبزق الآلة
الكردية العريقة الشعبية المعروفة بالطنبورة...
Shukri, who you are now seeing behind me, is now playing the
buzuq, the ancient popular Kurdish instrument known as the
tamboura...
عم يعزف هلق ألحان كردية.
He is now playing Kurdish melodies.
وموجود معه عدد من شباب ورجال الضيعة اللي شفناهم قبل شوي...
And present with him are a number of the young men and men
of the village whom we saw a little while ago...
رح نشوف شو عم يعزف وشو رح يغني ويمكن رح يرقصوا شوي، تابعونا.
We will see what he is playing and what he will sing, and
maybe they will dance a bit, follow us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام والإكرام، أهلاً وسهلاً.
And upon you be peace and honor, welcome.
ارتاحوا ارتاحوا.
Relax, relax.
يعطيك العافية يا أخو شكري.
May God give you health, brother Shukri.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
شو هاد اللي عزفتو هلق؟
What is this that you just played?
هي موال فلكلوري عفريني.
This is an Afrinian folkloric mawal.
شو اسمه؟
What is it called?
بيقولولو عيشة.
They call it Ayshe.
عيشة؟
Ayshe?
في موال غناء؟
Yes.
Is there a sung mawal?
إي والله في.
Yes, indeed there is.
هلق بتعزفلنا زينبة.
Now you will play Zeynabe for us.
زينبة.
Zeynabe.
شو معناتها يعني؟
What does it mean?
قديم فلكلوري.
An old folklore.
تمام، سمعنا.
Alright, let's hear it.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
شكرا إلك. رح نختم هلق معك،
Thank you. We will conclude with you now,
رح نودع السادة المشاهدين معك وإنت عم تعزف ع البزق.
we will bid farewell to the viewers with you while you are
playing the buzuq.
ورح أيضاً هنن يودعونا.
And they will also bid us farewell.
هلق بدي أعزف چفتتلي، هي كمان فلكلوري.
Now I want to play Çiftetelli, this is also folklore.
تفضل. رح نختم... نحن رح نختم وإنت عم تعزف.
Go ahead. We will conclude... we will conclude while you are
playing.
أعزائي المشاهدين، سنكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم في جولة جديدة
Dear viewers, we will be with you next week on a new tour
من قرية سورية أخرى حبيبة.
from another beloved Syrian village.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.